<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A funerall sermon, preached at the buriall of the Lady Iane Maitlane, daughter to the right noble earle, Iohn Earle of Lauderdail, at Hadington, the 19. of December. 1631. By Mr. I.M. Together with diverse epitaphs, aswell Latine, as English, written by sundry authors</title>
            <author>I. M., Mr.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1633</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 78 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 26 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A06686</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 17142</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S108302</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99843963</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99843963</idno>
            <idno type="VID">8734</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A06686)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 8734)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 850:04)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A funerall sermon, preached at the buriall of the Lady Iane Maitlane, daughter to the right noble earle, Iohn Earle of Lauderdail, at Hadington, the 19. of December. 1631. By Mr. I.M. Together with diverse epitaphs, aswell Latine, as English, written by sundry authors</title>
                  <author>I. M., Mr.</author>
                  <author>Maitland, John, fl. 1617-1637, attributed name.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 48, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by [R. Young] the printers to the Kings most excellent Majestie,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Edinburgh :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1633.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"Presumably by a J. Maitland"--STC.</note>
                  <note>Partly verse by various authors.</note>
                  <note>The last leaf is blank.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Maitland, Jean, --  Lady, 1612-1631 --  Poetry.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:8734:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:8734:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A FVNERALL SERMON, Preached at the buriall of the Lady <hi>Iane Maitlane,</hi> daughter to the Right Noble Earle, <hi>Iohn</hi> Earle of <hi>Lauderdail,</hi> at <hi>Hading<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton,</hi> the 19. of <hi>December.</hi> 1631.</p>
            <p>BY M. <hi>I. M.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Together with diverſe <hi>Epitaphs,</hi> aſ well <hi>Latine,</hi> as <hi>Engliſh,</hi> written by ſundry Authors.</p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>royal blazon as printer's device</figDesc>
               <p>IN MY DEFENCE GOD ME DEFEND</p>
            </figure>
            <p>
               <hi>EDINBVRGH,</hi> Printed by the <hi>Printers</hi> to the KINGS moſt excellent Majeſtie. 1633.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:8734:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:8734:2"/>
            <head>A FVNERALL SERMON PREACHED AT THE BURIALL of the Lady <hi>Iane</hi> MAITLANE.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>IOB. 14.14.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>All the daies of my appointed time will I wait, till my change come.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is ſaid, that it is better to be in the houſe of mourning, than mirth; if ever, I truſt now, you are in a houſe of mourning, and mourners; mourners, not ſo much with their doole, and mourning cloaths; as with mour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning hearts and weeping eyes. I pray God this mourning cauſed by this more than mournfull ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, may draw us to a mourning for our ſelves, and for our ſins. And that this change may leade us to the practiſe of <hi>Iob</hi> his reſolution here, <hi>All the dayes of my appointed time will I wait till my change come:</hi> I make it the ground of my ſpeech; ſince of a mour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner I muſt be a ſpeaker. Loth was I to it; But how ſhould I, how could I detrect it? this being the leaſt dutie I can; the laſt I ever ſhall perform to the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver-to-be-forgotten memory of this Honourable young Lady; Repreſſing therefore and ſmothering my own grief for a time; I will proceed having firſt called upon God, who onely can direct me, how to ſpeak, you how to hear, and both to his glory.</p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:8734:3"/>
            <p>THis <hi>change,</hi> to her als joyfull, as to us ſorrow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, cals upon us with <hi>Iob, all the dayes of our ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed time to wait till our change come.</hi> Few words, yet large matter; which at this time, is rather a trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, than an eaſe to the ſpeaker: of whom you can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not expect Scholaſtick ſpeculations, flowres of Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, broken ſentences of Poets; ſuch elaborate and painted diſcourſes as they, are more for ſhew than profit, ſo to this time altogether unſutable. It ſhall ſuffice me, if tempering my ſpeech with brevity &amp; perſpicuity, I can enforce upon you, the practiſe of what <hi>Iob</hi> reſolved, <hi>All the dayes of your appointed time to wait till your change come.</hi> And thus I enter upon my text by way of, 1. explication. 2. application. 3. exhortation. For explication, as I will not detain you with the dependence and deduction of the text; ſo I will not be curious in cutting and dividing the words: onely, in generall, I take them as running on three points, 1. <hi>Life,</hi> 2. <hi>Death,</hi> 3. <hi>Preparation in life for death.</hi> Of life you have two things; one expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed; That the time thereof is <hi>appointed;</hi> the other implied; That it is ſhort, rather to be meaſured by <hi>dayes</hi> than years. Death and the preparation there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, are ſet down in two words of large extent; death is a <hi>change,</hi> and our preparation a <hi>waiting for</hi> this <hi>change.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>☞ Our time is <hi>appointed,</hi> not by our ſelves, not by man, not by any other creature; but by the creator of all. His we are in our coming, ſtaying, leaving this world: from him is our <hi>time</hi> here, and <hi>change</hi> hence: what ever beſides, within us, without us, gets the name of prolonging our <hi>time,</hi> or haſting our
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:8734:3"/>
               <hi>change,</hi> it is ſubordinate to his <hi>appointment.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Our <hi>time</hi> is <hi>appointed:</hi> Some have years; ſome months; ſome dayes; ſome houres; all <hi>appointed,</hi> and meaſured forth by God. One comes to his <hi>change</hi> by a burning fever; another by a lingring con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption; one meets it in his bed, another in the ſtreet; thouſands at once in the field, and all by <hi>ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointment.</hi> If the ſparrows falling or flying, one haire of thy head it's growing or falling be <hi>appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted;</hi> how not our time and change by <hi>appointment?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. Our <hi>time</hi> is <hi>appointed</hi> by him who knowes what is beſt for him, what for us; our <hi>time</hi> is from him, and ſhould be for him: As our coming is not by chance, ſo neither our going. We are all ſet here for ſome buſines, which being done; then our <hi>appointed time</hi> leads to our <hi>change.</hi> Thus for the <hi>appointment</hi> of our time.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>All the dayes of my appointed time:</hi> Here the next, the brevitie of this time; a point ſo cleare by the light of Scripture, reaſon, and daily experience; that it might ſeeme a vain expenſe of our <hi>appointed time</hi> to inſiſt upon it. And ſurely if mens inward conceits, and outward practiſes did comply with their verball profeſſion, I ſhould wrong both you and my ſelfe, to make a pauſe here. But alaſſe, what ever be the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of the daies of our <hi>appointed time,</hi> yet I am ſure our carriage ſpeaks, that we dream not of <hi>dayes</hi> but of <hi>years,</hi> yea many years of our <hi>appointed time.</hi> Whence I intreat you is the caſting away of ſo much of our <hi>appointed time,</hi> in doing nothing, in do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing evill? whence the tyring of our wits to finde out new wayes to the ſpending thereof? whence the too-long
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:8734:4"/>ſpun-web of our ambitious, avaritious thoughts? whence thoſe many delayes, whereby we ſhift knowledge, repentance, faith? All grace and goodneſſe, and this <hi>waiting for our</hi> approaching <hi>change?</hi> whence all thoſe? but from our conceit not of <hi>dayes,</hi> but of <hi>years,</hi> not of ſhort, but long life? Yet the truth is, howſoever we may deceive and are deceived, <hi>Iobs</hi> words muſt ſtand <hi>(All the dayes of my appointed time)</hi> ſpoken by a man of truth, and inſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by the ſpirit of truth.</p>
            <p>Scripture is ſo copious in this argument, that hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly can you turn over many pages, but you will meet with one or other paſſage or word ſounding this way. Neither onely will you finde poſitive ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, but great varietie of reſemblances, whereby Gods Spirit would ſet forth theſe daies, or ſhortnes of our <hi>appointed time.</hi> Hence theſe compariſons, of a flower, a ſhadow, a vapour appearing for a while, and then vaniſhing, a dream, an Eagles flight in the aire, a cloud blown away with the winde, or elſe diſſolved; a ſpan meaſured in an inſtant, with many ſuch like: <hi>David</hi> cals it vanitie, which is nothing; yea not onely his time and dayes, but him ſelfe, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of them; <hi>Every man in his beſt eſtate is altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther vanitie, Pſal.</hi> 39.5. where each word is empha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticke, man, every man, every man in his beſt eſtate, is vanitie, is altogether vanitie: And <hi>Pſal.</hi> 62.9. <hi>The children of men are vanitie, the chief men are lyes; to lay them upon a balance they are altogether lighter than vanitie:</hi> And how I pray you can we count that long, which is in continuall conſumption; the more time we have, the nearer we are to our <hi>change;</hi>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:8734:4"/>yea <hi>our change</hi> begins in a manner with <hi>our time;</hi> no ſooner living than beginning to die: Yeſterday is not to be recalled, what is paſt is periſhed; the ſhadow of our time is ſtill in motion; this glaſſe ſtill run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning; this ſhip ſtill ſayling; while we are eating, drin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king, ſleeping, walking, talking, we are ſtill carried to <hi>this change;</hi> and to cloſe this point; there is nothing makes our time ſeeme long, but the expectation of hope of long time; and the longeſt time, once paſſed, is but a dream, but vanitie.</p>
            <p>Thus of life, as <hi>appointed</hi> by God; as meaſured by <hi>dayes;</hi> The other two points of our <hi>change,</hi> and <hi>wai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting for this change,</hi> is matter for many ſermons, and a task for our whole life; But within this ſhort ſcantling of time, wherewith I am ſtraitned, I ſhall abſolve them in two words. The <hi>change</hi> we muſt <hi>wait for,</hi> is that which is begun by death, and is ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſhed at our reſurrection; O how joyfull, how glorious a change to the godly; whoſe corruption puts on incorruption, whoſe mortality puts on im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortality; who are <hi>changed</hi> and tranſchanged into the glory of God. This <hi>happy change</hi> we muſt wait for; Firſt, by practiſe, living ſo as we may attain to it. Secondly, by meditation, thinking on it ere it come. Thirdly, by reſolution embracing it when it comes; I haſten to the application.</p>
            <p>Works move more than words, teaching by ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emple is more effectuall than by diſcourſe. If the ardent, and affectionat deſires of her Honourable pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, the hearty wiſhes of her many worthy friends; the many ſalt tears, ſobs, ſighes, groanes, of all her acquaintance, the prayers and ſupplications of us all;
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:8734:5"/>if gifts of body and minde ſurpaſſing ordinarie, and ſtirring almoſt admiration in the beholders; if all thoſe could have delayed this <hi>change,</hi> neither ſhould your eyes have ſeene, nor my tongue this day ſpoken of it; but it was <hi>appointed</hi> by God, bleſſed be his name; his will, not ours, be done.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Maximilian,</hi> the firſt of that name, commanded that his dead body ſhould be expoſed to publique view; adding this reaſon, <hi>ut vel meo diſcant exemplo.</hi> Behold we have this day propoſed our <hi>Maxima,</hi> the choyceſt jewell we had, once the delight of our eyes, and the joy of our hearts; her we propoſed a ſpecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle, not to be gazed upon, but that in this <hi>change</hi> ye might read a lecture of <hi>your own coming change;</hi> It is I know expected I ſhould ſpeake ſomewhat of her; and why ſhould I fruſtrat your expectation? for though theſe ſpeeches ſhould not be Panegyricks, onely for the praiſes of the dead; but rather inſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons for the living; yet I ſee not why their due com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandations, becauſe of their excellent vertues, ſhould be ſuppreſſed; ſince God, in them, by them, is glorified, others edified. And hath not the holy Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit told us, that, <hi>As the memorie of the wicked ſhall rot, ſo the memorie of the juſt ſhall be bleſſed.</hi> Prov. 10.7. <hi>The righteous ſhall be had in everlaſting remembrance,</hi> Pſal. 112.6. If with God, why not with man?</p>
            <p>Having upon thoſe grounds reſolved to ſpeake of her, yet ſo, as the truth of my love, ſhould not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judge my love of truth; ſtill for a time I remained irreſolved what to ſpeake, where to begin, when to end; <hi>inopem me copia fecit.</hi> In end I found that, as to ſpeake nothing were intolerable, ſo to ſpeak all were
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:8734:5"/>impoſſible: So that my courſe muſt be of many things to make choyce of ſome few; and that by confining my ſpeech to my text, 1. of <hi>her dayes;</hi> 2. of <hi>her appointed time;</hi> 3. <hi>her change;</hi> 4. <hi>her wai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting for her change. All the dayes of her appointed time did ſhe wait till her change came.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>All the dayes.</hi> Sometimes dayes are taken for years, and years for dayes; when I ſpeake of her time, I doubt whether to ſay dayes, or years: Let me joyn them both; all the dayes, all the years: Her appointed time was dayes, her appointed time was years; it was ſhort, it was long. Will we take time and dayes as they are ordinarily; alaſſe then I muſt ſay ſhe had dayes, and but few dayes that was worthy of years, of many years; thouſands who abuſe their <hi>time</hi> to the diſhonour of God, them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, the world, have <hi>many dayes;</hi> while ſhe, who knew both what time was, and how to uſe time, had but few. Ah what pitty to behold ſuch a bloſſome blaſted in the ſpring? ſuch a flower withered in the morning? ſuch a bright and glancing ſtarre over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clouded with a gloomie and tempeſtuous night. But if we ſhall call thoſe onely dayes that are ſpent ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourably, vertuouſly, religiouſly, then I may boldly turn dayes into years, and ſay, all the years <hi>of her appointed time.</hi> Her time was not ſhort, but long. <hi>Diu vixit, licet non diu fuit,</hi> She lived long in a ſhort time; is one day of a mans life governed with knowledge and reaſon, to be prized above the many years of the unreaſonable creature? why not her few dayes full of knowledge and grace to be valued beyond the longeſt time of too too many, who at
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:8734:6"/>foure times twenty come to their change emptie of both? if <hi>her few dayes</hi> breed ſorrow, let <hi>her many years</hi> bring us comfort.</p>
            <p>Her time was <hi>Appointed by God;</hi> here a ground of patience. Since this change, the affections and paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions of many have ſhown themſelves, and ſtill doth; The eyes of all who knew her, the tongues of all who heard of her do abundantly teſtifie, not a private but a publique ſorrow: and ſhall we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn that, which God and Nature commands? Chriſt and his Saints practiſed it. We finde the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triarches and holy men mourning over their dead: our bleſſed Saviour ſhedding teares over <hi>Lazarus;</hi> and ſhall it then be ſtrange if we behold her worthy parents lifting up their voyces with cryes, being de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prived of ſuch a divided peece of themſelves? Her honourable friends to bedeaw their cheeks, being robbed of ſuch a choyce flower of their garland? all her acquaintance, familiars, and followers, to fill heaven and earth with their lamentations? wanting her, whoſe injoying was a great part of their earthly joy? yea, and it is ſtrange to ſee all thoſe bounds wher ſhe was known by eye or eare, to mourn; each family, as if they were mourning for their own firſt born, being fruſtrat of thoſe great hopes, and common benefits, her few dayes did promiſe to all? Surely it is not ſtrange, nor can be blamed. And to increaſe it by patheticke ſpeeches, I neither can, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing already at ſuch a hight; neither will, leaſt we give too large reines to it. Not to mourn, is not onely graceleſſe, but unnaturall; to be immoderate in our mourning is not Chriſtian, but Heatheniſh.
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:8734:6"/>When <hi>Iacob</hi> came to his <hi>change, Ioſeph</hi> mourned; ſo did the <hi>Egytians;</hi> he but 7. dayes, they 70. <hi>Gen.</hi> 50.3.10. He knew his time was <hi>appointed</hi> by God, they looked to fate, and neceſſity: he knew his death was but a <hi>change,</hi> they tooke it for a finall diſſolution and deſtruction. Mourn then we may, we ſhould, but to exceed in our <hi>mourning as thoſe who have no hope,</hi> we may not, we ſhould not. And here among many, one ground for the moderation of our ſorrow, and perſwading of patience, <hi>Her time was appointed of God:</hi> if it had been poſſible that another ſhould have wrought this <hi>change;</hi> would we, think ye, have taken it patiently? no, rather would we have parted with our own eyes. But now, O Lord, thou haſt done it, and therefore with thy ſervant <hi>David</hi> we muſt cloſe our mouth, yea reverence, obey, glorifie thy appointment, <hi>juſt are all thy ordinances, upright are all thy wayes:</hi> Though before with <hi>David</hi> we did weep, and would not be comforted, yet now ſeeing the evidence of thy appointment, we muſt riſe up and praiſe thee.</p>
            <p>Ye ſee her <hi>appointed time:</hi> I come now to her <hi>wai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting. Iob</hi> ſaith, he would <hi>wait for his change,</hi> and why may not I ſay, <hi>All her dayes ſhe did wait till her change came.</hi> For if the <hi>waiting</hi> for our <hi>change</hi> be; firſt, the leading of ſuch a life as doth ſhew, we know there will be a <hi>change;</hi> ſecondly, if it be in the confluence of worldly bleſſings, to minde more our <hi>change</hi> than them; thirdly, if it be, at the approaching thereof, to deſire it, embrace it, welcome it, joy in it, then I may truly ſay, <hi>ſhe did wait for her change.</hi> God is my witneſſe, what I ſpeak, it is not from partiall affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:8734:7"/>ſo it is not for particular ends. I follow not doubtfull rumours, uncertain and flying reports; but what I know to be truth from her birth to this her change, from her cradle to her grave; I ſpeake and that for truths ſake; ſetting <hi>her waiting</hi> for a pattern to <hi>our waiting.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt then, I ſay, her life was ſuch as did teſtifie ſhe knew there would be a <hi>change.</hi> Religion, piety, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votion is that, which gives, as it were, another life to all morall vertues, and makes them Chriſtian, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out it they may be profitable to others, but little to our ſelves. It is true, onely God knowes the heart in it ſelf, and by himſelf: but if pregnant preſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and well nigh infallible ſignes may be a firme ground for paſſing cenſure; I may confidently af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme and aſſevere, that the fear of God was placed, yea deeply rooted in her heart: and from this foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain did flow thoſe ſtreames of the exerciſe of reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion; Her hunger, and burning deſire to hear Gods word, her attention in hearing, her knowledge by hearing, her ſweet devout communication and practiſe after hearing; What? ſhall I name to you her frequent praying; daily reading; her writing al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt the whole New Teſtament with her own hand: and was all onely in hypocriſie, and for ſhew? No, I am aſſured her religion was not ſo much in her eares and tongue (as it is with many) as in her heart and life. Who knew her, knowes ſhe was more in ſubſtance than in ſhow. From this ſame fountain flowed alſo that rare, and ſcarce to be matched obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, love, honour, and all due reſpect to her pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents; which as her whole life did witneſſe, ſo her
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:8734:7"/>
               <hi>change:</hi> nothing more grieving her for <hi>her change,</hi> as that <hi>her change</hi> would bring grief to them. If I ſhould enlarge her obſervance to her ſuperiours in regard of age and ſtate of life, her dutifull reſpect to her equals, her modeſt &amp; moderat carriage to her in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feriors; her love to all, and love of all; I might eaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly wearie my ſelf in relating, and you in hearing. The mouths of many will ſpeak what now I may not, onely two words: It is rare to finde ſo few years ſo full of nature, ſo full of grace: And next whereas ſuch eminent parts and vertues, eſpecially in young years, are uſually accompanied, yea and darkned with more than conſpicuous faults: I know many will bear witneſſe with me, that not onely ſhe was free of ſuch as might any wayes obſcure her more noble parts; but even of ſuch as might bring upon her the leaſt ſtain before man, being blameleſſe (far be it from me to ſay before God) I am ſure be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the world. Now judge yee if ſuch a life was not a <hi>waiting for her change?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For the ſecond, The confluence of worldly bleſſings; I confeſſe my ignorance in Herauldry, to deſcribe her pedigree and deſcent, derived by many generati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons from her well deſerving anceſtors. Onely this I can ſay (and let me ſay it to provoke their poſteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to imitation and emulation) they were truly ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable, ſince both blood and vertue joyned to make them noble: noble not onely by inheritance, but by purchaſe: Their greatneſſe from their blood, their goodnes was from their vertue. Such her birth. But what availes names, titles, armes, honours, if there be no more? her birth did not ſo much honour
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:8734:8"/>her, as ſhe it; having in a beautifull body a more beautifull ſoule; ſuch knowledge, wiſedome, skill in all things befitting her ſex, and far above her age<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> that ſcarſe her equall, let be her ſuperiour could be found. Why ſhould I ſpeak to you of her many noble friends, her meanes and worldly eſtate, and hopes, and ſuch like. And thoſe alſo are Gods bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings, not to be neglected, and by many too much reſpected: Now what could have been expected, but that this concurrence of earthly bleſſings of all ſorts, within, without, of birth, body, ſoul, eſtate, friends, would have tied her heart to the world, and raiſed her thoughts to an applauding of her ſelf, and contemning of others? But ah! who ever did ſee pride ſhine in thoſe eyes? when did ever neglect and contempt ſhew it ſelf, in that meek, loving, and lovly countenance? I have often wondered to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold ſuch excellent parts followed with ſuch admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable humility, humanity, modeſty, curtiſie: and that not onely towards the great (which may, and often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times dwels with pride) but even to thoſe of the lower ſort. Now what did all this ſhew? but that her heart was not in this world; that thoſe worm-eaten and fading pleaſures did not bewitch her; that ſhe did thinke on her <hi>change;</hi> and that trampling un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der foot all the pompe and glory of this world, ſhe did aſpire to that glory, the eye never ſaw, the eare never heard?</p>
            <p>Thirdly, when her weakneſſe did threaten her <hi>change;</hi> with what ſpirituall courage did ſhe wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come it? Thouſands dare not ſo much as once think on their <hi>change:</hi> The Athieſt, the Epicure, the
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:8734:8"/>worldling are confounded with the apprehenſion thereof: Onely the child of God dareth encounter it. Her ſtrength was from God, whom ſhe did ply, and importune with ardent prayers to ſtrengthen and confirm her in her laſt conflict. Her inward friends, a good conſcience, and faith in Chriſt did ſuſtain her; and made that as ſhe was not aſhamed to live, ſo not afraid to die.</p>
            <p>The laſt word of my text, and of her, is <hi>her change;</hi> O bitter-ſweet <hi>change!</hi> bitter to us, ſweet to her. To us bitter, who ſhall ſee no more that face, nor hear that voyce, we never ſaw nor heard, but with plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, and joy! bitter to us, who by this <hi>change</hi> have our joy <hi>changed</hi> into ſorrow, our laughter into mour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning! but ô ſweet, ô <hi>joyfull change</hi> to her! who here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by hath <hi>changed</hi> earth for heaven, the place of her exile for her fathers houſe; where there be many manſions: the company of mortall men, with the happy fellowſhip of the immortall God, of Chriſt her Saviour, of the glorious Angels, and bleſſed ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits of the juſt! Her <hi>change</hi> like the furnace of fire to the three children, at the worſt hath but looſed her bands; like <hi>Ionah's whale</hi> carried her through the ſtorms of this tempeſtuous world to the port of her eternall reſt; like <hi>the red Sea</hi> hath opened her a paſſage from this Egypt to that heavenly Caanan. Her then we neither do, nor can bewaile, whoſe <hi>change</hi> hath <hi>changed</hi> her to joy without <hi>change:</hi> but we may, we do bewaile our ſelves; we bewaile our owne loſe; the dolefull memory whereof ſome of us I hope will ever carry about, aye untill our own <hi>change</hi> come.</p>
            <pb n="14" facs="tcp:8734:9"/>
            <p>I have done with my application, wherein if any ſhall think I have ſpoken too much, yet I will think too little; and I hope there is none, to whom ſhe was known, but knows that I have keeped within bounds, and will blame perhaps my defect rather than exceſſe.</p>
            <p>I come to the laſt thing I purpoſed: The exhorta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Right honourable, right worthy, and dearely beloved; you have heard of <hi>Iob his change;</hi> and now ſee this: Let me tell you that ere long, there is not any of us, who are here, but he ſhall come to his own <hi>change.</hi> Here indeed we have diſtinctions of ſtates, callings, perſons, and that juſtly; but <hi>Pallida mors,</hi> this <hi>change</hi> doth equall all; you know the compari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the cheſſe-men, while the play laſteth, there is diſtinction of them; being eſteemed as they may beſt ſerve our purpoſe; but the play ended, and chek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mete given, all promiſcuouſly are hurled in the box; and often the leaſt lies above the greateſt: So here, though men be more or leſſe regarded in reſpect of the foreſaid differences; yet when this <hi>change</hi> comes, whereby the play of this life is ended, then we are equally hurled in the grave, and often the poore mans duſt lies above the rich. When ye behold a heap of bones, who can ſay, here are the rich mans, there the poor's? Oh! if we could obtain ſo much liberty and leaſure of our too too many reſtleſſe and unprofitable thoughts, as to make this <hi>change</hi> a great part of our daily meditation! We need not <hi>Philip's</hi> monitor, nor a dead mans ſkull uſed by the Egypti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, to be our <hi>memento;</hi> each place, day, perſon will do it. And yet alaſſe, though nothing be more ſeene,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:8734:9"/>and better known, nothing is leſſe thought upon: ſuch a <hi>change</hi> as this, may poſſibly enforce us to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flect our thoughts upon our ſelves, and <hi>our own ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaching change;</hi> but ah! how ſhort, how evaniſhing, how ineffectuall are thoſe thoughts! one moment often giving them both life and death? But I may not treſpaſſe too far upon your patience in preſſing this argument. Let me with ſome brief collections reſume my text and leave.</p>
            <p>Is our <hi>time</hi> but <hi>dayes?</hi> Firſt, how may we not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wail the by-gone, that ſo much of ſo ſhort time ſhould have been ſo evil imployed? And ſecondly, why are we not carefull to manage that which is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maining. Thirdly, you have taſted of all thoſe fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding pleaſures, the world doth either promiſe, or can give; experience hath made you ſee their vanity, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing but like yeſter-nights dream. Why then ſhould <hi>our few dayes</hi> be taken up any longer with that, which we know in the end will bring us nothing, but late repentance? Fourthly, <hi>our time</hi> is ſhort, and yet upon this day, this houre, this moment of our life, depends an eternity either of pleaſure or pain. What madneſſe to purchaſe eternall pain for a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments ſeeming pleaſure? Fiftly, <hi>Methuſhalem</hi> his dayes were too few either to expreſſe our ſorrow for ſinne, or thankfulneſſe for Gods mercies: How then ſhould we not be circumſpect ſo to governe thoſe <hi>few dayes of our appointed time,</hi> that not one day, not one houre may paſſe, without doing that we never can do ſufficiently?</p>
            <p>The <hi>dayes of our appointed time</hi> are uncertain? <hi>Iob</hi> ſaith, <hi>all the dayes,</hi> but he tels not how many; he
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:8734:10"/>profeſſes, <hi>he will wait till his change come;</hi> but knew not, when it would come: And is not his caſe herein, ours alſo? Yes certainly. Who knowes but this day may end his daies; and your <hi>change</hi> may meet you ere you meet with your houſes; how ſhould this ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſten our repentance? our amendment? We are al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes reſolving and ſtill unreſolved; what projects, what purpoſes tending to reformation of our lives have vaniſhed in the aire? O when ſhall we begin to do that, the not doing whereof will make us undone? Your time is uncertain here; and what if this <hi>change</hi> of your bodies preveen the <hi>change</hi> of your ſoules? Oh beloved, delay not longer; How many are in hell who had thoſe fleeting and flying motions of repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance and reformation, that ſome of you now have? but poſtponing them, this <hi>change</hi> interveened, and brought a dolefull <hi>change</hi> upon them. Let not, I in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treat you, a matter of ſuch conſequence, as the eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall ſalvation of your ſoules be caſten off to future time which is ſo uncertain.</p>
            <p>Our <hi>change</hi> is certain and common. If with <hi>Abel</hi> we had no precedent examples thereof, our <hi>not wai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting</hi> were in ſome ſort tolerable; but now in this ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall condition of all mankind, whereby they are lyable to this <hi>change,</hi> what can we pretend for our egregious ſlackneſſe and remiſneſſe that will not thus <hi>change</hi> in our thoughts, before it ſeaze on our bodies. Doth the earth-worme take his <hi>change</hi> to heart? no: then he would not waſte his body, minde, conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, ſo exceſſively, for the heaping together the traſh of this earth; ſince by this <hi>change</hi> he will be ſtripped of all? Doth the thought hereof bereave
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:8734:10"/>the aſpiring ſpirit of its reſt? no: then he would not ſo beat his braines, ſpend his wits, that he may raiſe himſelf though upon the ruine of his betters: ſince by this <hi>change</hi> he muſt once be troden under foot, and have all his earthly <hi>glory laid in the duſt.</hi> But I muſt end. I pray God this <hi>change</hi> may teach us, <hi>all the dayes of our appointed time to wait, till our change come.</hi> (<g ref="char:dtristar">*⁎*</g>)</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="elegies">
            <pb facs="tcp:8734:11"/>
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:8734:11"/>
            <head>IN OBITUM NOBILISSIMAE Virginis JANAE METELLANAE, filiae Comitis Lauderi.</head>
            <div type="elegy">
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">Q</seg>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>arta</hi> Metellanam <hi>ſubtraxit olympias orbi,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Spem procerum, patrii deliciaſque ſoli.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Ante Deae quàm Juno ſuos accenderet ignes,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Barbara Lethaeis Atropos hauſit aquis.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Quid querar? urticis fas eſt ſperare ſenectam,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Lappa nec hybernas deperit ante nives;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Sed violas, teneraſque roſas, &amp; candida prati</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Lilia, vere vides ſurgere, vere mori.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <head>Aliud,</head>
                  <l>
                     <hi>C<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>itria debuerat largiri ſecla, puellam</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Parca</hi> Metellanam <hi>poſt tria luſtra rapit.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Virtutes numer at Lacheſis, non ſupputat annos;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Fructus erat praecox, carptus &amp; ante diem.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <signed>Arturus Jonſtonus.</signed>
            </div>
            <div type="elegy">
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Coeleſtes animi dotes producere poſſent</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Si vitam, procul &amp; mortis depellere tela;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Omnes, Diva, tibi vidiſſes funere Nymphas</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Praereptas, maeſtae quae nunc tua funera deflent:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Verùm aliter viſum ſuperis: properantia fata</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Coeleſtes rapiunt regnae ad coeleſtia mentes:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Nec patitur Coeli clementia, prima lutoſis</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Ornamenta poli terrarum haerere lacunis.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <signed>Joannes Adamſonus.</signed>
            </div>
            <div type="elegy">
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:8734:12"/>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>PAlladium Veſtaeflagrante ex aede Metellus</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Suſtulit, è medjis eripuit<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> focis.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Veſta memor facti, ſervatorìſ<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> Minervae,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Jure</hi> Metellanis <hi>ſemper amica fuit.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Hanc ìgitur caſtam rapuit de gente Metelli,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Aeternâ ut poſſit virginitate fruì.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Et ſibi quòd data ſit fatis tutela Decembris,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Mortalis vitae terminus ille fuit.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <signed>G. Jonſtonus. M. D.</signed>
            </div>
            <div type="elegy">
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Hâc voti menſura hominum componitur urnâ,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Et deſiderij meta ſupremajacet.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Si generis ſeries placet, haec milleſima claros</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Cenſebat longo ſanguine gentis avos:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Si decor, &amp; niveo delectat gratia vultu,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Aemula certabant Cypridos ora Deae:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Si dos ampla juvat, ſuperabant munera matri</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Et patri, Attaticae quas numeraret opes,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Dulcius argutas pulſabat Apolline chordas,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Doctius &amp; Phrygiâ Pallade pinxit acu.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Dextera non aliter ſignavit arundine voces,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Quàm quae chalchographis charta notata typis.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Virtute aequales ſuperavit, Cynthia quantum</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Exiguas, pleno cum nitet orbe, faces.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nde licet matura viro, quia lege maritâ</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Nullus erat tantos dignus inire toros,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Connubio Deus ipſe ſibi ſociavit in aevum,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Et fruitur ſponſo, nunc ſuper aſtrae, Deo.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Defuncta matrem conſolatur.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>DEſine chara parens, mordaci pectora luctu</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Etgemitu manes ſollicitare meos.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <pb n="21" facs="tcp:8734:12"/>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Immaturatibi videor cecidiſſe juventâ,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Alba velut primo flore liguſtra cadunt:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Sed cita mors citius patrio quia reddit Olympo,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Mitte queri vitae de brevitate meae.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Exilium breve, vita brevis, cûi longior aetas,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Longius exilij taedia lenta tulit.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <signed>M. Andr. Ramſaeus.</signed>
            </div>
            <div type="elegy">
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>ECce</hi> Metellanae <hi>tumulum, quo condita virgo,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Vix vicena cui bruma peracta, jacet,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Si proavos ſpectes memoranda<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> ſtemmata, vixit</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Illa</hi> Metellanae <hi>ſtirpſ<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> decuſ<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> domus;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Si dotes, ſuperûm demiſſam ſedibus, ipſis</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>A ſuperis artes addidiciſſe reor.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Terpſichore docuit citharae percurrere nerves</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Pectine, &amp; ad dulces verbareferre modos:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Ardentes auro veſtes oſtro<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> ſuperbo</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Ipſa dedit Phrygiâ pingere Pallas acu,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Quin inter ſtellas ut Cynthia fulget, ut inter</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Nimpharum virides Deïopeia choros;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Omnes huic decus eximium ſpeciem<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> decoram</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Aequales ſupra contulit alma Venus.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Certat at egregiae virtus dum vivida formae,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lterius nec quo progrediatur habet.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Huc propera, huc virgo propera, Deus inquit, ad aſtrae</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Inclyta te revocat ſortis origo tuae.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <signed>Da. Wedderburnus</signed>
            </div>
            <div type="elegy">
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>REge</hi> Metellano <hi>(ſcriptorum ut conſona vox eſt)</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Natus erat noſtri fons &amp; origo boni;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <pb n="22" facs="tcp:8734:13"/>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Natus erat</hi> Chriſtus, <hi>quo ductum ſtemmate nomen</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Cernimus in noſtros invaluiſſe dies.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Jam<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> cluit veteris flos, &amp; nova gloria gentis,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Teſtis ades patrii gemma,</hi> Ladere, <hi>ſoli;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Teſtis</hi> Joanna <hi>es: tibi gratum ut gratia nomen,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Rem<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> dedit, tanto nomini &amp; eſſe parem.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Si<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> queam propriè communia dicere, ſi<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan>
                     </hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>In re tantâ animi promere ſenſa mei:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Jure</hi> Metellanae <hi>pariter cognomine gaudes:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Ritè quadrat donis vox ita facta tuis,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>tenes: Deus eſt cognominis author;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>animae tot dedit alma tuae.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Virgo<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> virginibus jam regnas inſita divis:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Fallitur interitum mors meditata tuum.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Vita tibi eſt</hi> Chriſtus, <hi>cujus tot ſancta ſuperſunt</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Dogmata, Daedaliâ quae tibi picta manu.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Sit tibi, ſit certet quae ſtemmate, rarior aequâ</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Ornabit morum nobilitate genus.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <signed>M. Patricius Sandeus.</signed>
            </div>
            <div type="elegy">
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>RApta jacet primis hîc</hi> Metellana <hi>ſub annis</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Flebilis, &amp; maeſtis virgo cienda modis:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Carpere quì tenerum Parcae potuiſtis amomum?</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Non puduit tantum conviolaſſe decus?</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Nectare virgineam Nymphae lachrimiſ<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> favillam</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Spargite; perpetuo floreat urna croc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Vos cineri date juſta pio, conferte corollas;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Haec redeat veſtris annua cura choris.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <signed>Patr. Panterus.</signed>
            </div>
            <div type="elegy">
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:8734:13"/>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>FLete</hi> Metellanae <hi>cineres qui cernitis urnam,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Flete puellares, funereaſ<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> faces.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Herois ſoboles, &amp; tanto digna parente,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Cui<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> pari genitrix auxit honore genus:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>t generis clari, ſic clarum exemplar honeſti,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Virgo in virgineo gloria prima choro;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Dotibus ingenij dives, decoravit eaſdem</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Artibus ingenuis, excoluit<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> labor.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Aſt eadem quae lima animum terit, atterit annos,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Cura coquit teneras &amp; philomuſa dies.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Ante annos ſciviſſe nocet, completa<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> virtus</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Fecerat, ut Clotho crederet eſſe ſenem.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Prima ſui ſecli, coelo<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> futura ſecunda,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Virginis Erigones virgo recepta ſinu.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Virginis &amp; laudes ductas meliore metallo,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Publica perpetuo fama tenore ſonat.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Fama virtutum, tuba ſempiterna.</hi>
               </l>
               <lg>
                  <head>Aliud.</head>
                  <l>
                     <hi>MArmoreus niſi ſit, quae marmore conditur iſte,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Lectori lachrimas lecta movere poteſt.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Scilicet una, cui melos &amp; myrothecion omne,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Sais &amp; Aonidum ſacra caterva dedit:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>na bonis animi, fortunae, corporis aucta,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Quae data ſunt alijs ſingula, cuncta tulit.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Altera, ſed melior, meritó Pandora Deorum,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Verſibus Aſcraeis altera digna novis.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>t<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> ſuo ſimilem, genuit vix Roma Metello,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Noſtra</hi> Metellanae <hi>nec tulit ora parem.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Eximiae eximio tot in uno corpore dotes,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Secula Cumaeae promeruere ſenis.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Sed brevis immodicis aetas, &amp; rara ſenectus,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Et citò ſaepe ſolent optima quae<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> rapi.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Hoc decus, aetatis decas altera vexit ad aſtra,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Foelix quae coelo tam cito digna fuit.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <pb n="24" facs="tcp:8734:14"/>
                  <head>Ad defunctam.</head>
                  <l>
                     <hi>PRima puellarum quas priſca aut noſtra tulerunt,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Quaſ<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> Caledonijs ſecla futura dabunt;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Parce, nec ista tibi veluti data justa putato,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Sed tanquam moestas manibus inferias.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Memoriae &amp; amoris ergo</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Moerens moestuſ<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> parentavit</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <signed>Galt. Bellendinus.</signed>
            </div>
            <div type="elegy">
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Q<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ae Venus huc taedas debebas ferre jugales,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Funereas quid das, heu Libitina, faces?</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſque adeo Idaeae remanent veſtigia rixae,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Pallada nec cauſâ eſt hac cecidiſſe ſatis.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Palladium medio rapuit ſi ex igne Metellus,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Lumine non fuerat captus utro<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> pius.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Illa</hi> Metellanam <hi>tanto poſt tempore neptem</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Invidia, &amp; te nunc opprimis atra Venus.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>(Is decor oris erat, roſeiſ<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> affuſa labellis</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Gratia; non occulos unus obibat amor.)</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Sed doluit Cytheraea ſuas in corpore dotes</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Infra Cecropiae dona jacêre Deae.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Quippe parem priſcae noſtram ſtuduere tribuli</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Fingere Caeciliam nata ſoro<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> Jovis.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Pronuba quod deerat, quaerebat Juno maritum</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Jungere quem merita eſt Tarquinio<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> parem.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Invidit non caſta <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>enus, quia Palladis artes</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Et genium edidicit; pro face fax<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> data eſt.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Fax<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan>
                     </hi> Metellanae <hi>gratiſſima, quippe maritum</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Perpetua accepit ſic ea virgo Deum.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:8734:14"/>
               <lg>
                  <head>Aliud.</head>
                  <l>
                     <hi>FRuſtra qui Numidas, fruſtra qui regna Philippi</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Cognatus domuit, marmor ebur<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> paret.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Non Lybicum quaero tumulum, non ſaxa Laconum,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Nec quae huc Dalmaticus flavametalla vehat.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſ<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> ſequor Judae coeleſtem virgo leonem,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Et me viventum circulus unus habet.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <signed>R. Magillus Juris et aequi ſtudioſus,</signed>
            </div>
            <div type="elegy">
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Q<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ae cantu Euterpe, quae juncta ſororibus ipſa</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Terpſichore, &amp; plectro magnus Apollo poteſt:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Aut quas faemineis animis impendere dotes</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Vel natura, vel ars ingenioſa ſolet;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>His majora habuit, cujus modo ſtamina vitae</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Abrupit Lacheſis; tam cito rara cadunt!</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Heu pietas coelum petyt, pudicitia, forma,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Nobilitas, virtus, Palladis ingenium.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Sed veluti brumâ pereuntia, vere reſurgunt;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Sic ea perpetuo flore renata viget.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <signed>L. J. M.</signed>
            </div>
            <div type="elegy">
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Q<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>od coelum tenuit pulchri, quod terra boni<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan>,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Metlana <hi>in gremium tranſijt omne tuum.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Quae poterat, major conceſſerat omnia mundus,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Nec potuit mundus plura tenere minor.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Religio veram te oſtenderat Heroinam,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Tradiderat virtus &amp; diadema ſuum.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <pb n="26" facs="tcp:8734:15"/>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Divinae varias decoraſti Palladis artes,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Et muſae gazas jure dedere ſuas.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Stemma vetus, comitas, caſti<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> modeſtia vultus,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Cogebant hominum lumina, corda ſequi.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Sed mors humanas non curas ferrea curas;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Nil coeli aut terrae dona ſtupenda movent.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>At quantùm noſtros contemnis, ſaeva dolores,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Tantùm Nympha minas negligit iſta tuas.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Avolat in patriam (te ſpretâ) nobilis aulam;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Dilacerat nobis triſtia corda abitus.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Hou nimium mors te fecerunt fata potentem,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Quid! peſſum tantae virginis ora dari?</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Colla jugo juvenis, dat colla &amp; eburnea virgo,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Ergo te contra nullus aſylus erit.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Evaſere ungues, Pietas, virtuſ<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> rapaces,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Quae<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> bonas animas gloria tuta manet.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Laeta dies veniet, quâ tu moriere viciſſim,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Tum genus in noſtrum vana tyrannis erit.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Sed quid ego laudes aut vota effundere coner?</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Te Deus auricomus carmina digna canat.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Sat miſero vatijuſtum narraſſe dolorem,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Flebile ſat miſeno ſit ceciniſſe melos.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Plura vetat vulnus, moerenti<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> obstruit ora,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Garrit cura levis, cura cruenta ſtupet.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <head>Aliud.</head>
                  <l>WHat goodneſſe, beauty, heaven and earth embowr'd</l>
                  <l>(Sweet Lady) upon Thee it all was powr'd</l>
                  <l>All which it could, the greater world thee gave,</l>
                  <l>And more no little world did e're receive,</l>
                  <l>Thee above all, religion did adorn,</l>
                  <l>And vertues crown was duely by thee born;</l>
                  <l>Divine Minerva's artes by thee were grac'd;</l>
                  <l>The Muſes in their throne thee juſtly plac'd.</l>
                  <pb n="27" facs="tcp:8734:15"/>
                  <l>Birth, courteſie, ſweet modeſty and grace</l>
                  <l>Of eyes and hearts made thee the reſting place.</l>
                  <l>But yron death contemning all our pleaſures,</l>
                  <l>Of heaven and earth regarded not the treaſures:</l>
                  <l>Yet if thou little didſt our groans reſpect,</l>
                  <l>(Grim ghoſt) this Nymphe too did thy threats neglect:</l>
                  <l>To heaven her long'd-for ſoil (thoughtleſſe of thee)</l>
                  <l>Shee flees, and leaves us in ſad miſery.</l>
                  <l>Alas? the Fates to thee have given hudge might;</l>
                  <l>That ſuch a vergin lies bereft of light.</l>
                  <l>Maids iv'rie necks, and young mens all do yeeld</l>
                  <l>Unto thy yoke, againſt thee ſerves no ſheeld.</l>
                  <l>Yet, vertue, glory, (though thou all devoure)</l>
                  <l>And piety are not thralled to thy power.</l>
                  <l>That day haſtes on, when of thy tyranny</l>
                  <l>O're man, the binding cordes ſhall broken be:</l>
                  <l>Till then, you fragrant noble flowers attend</l>
                  <l>This monument, and here your pow'rs extend.</l>
                  <l>And gems (heavens tears) bewailing ſtars, diſtill</l>
                  <l>Both day and night upon theſe aſhes ſtill.</l>
                  <l>I will not touch thy praiſes (noble dame)</l>
                  <l>The prince of poets ſhould proclaim the ſame:</l>
                  <l>My juſt and bleeding grief I only ſhow,</l>
                  <l>And ſome faint elegie thereon beſtow.</l>
                  <l>Soreneſſe of wound bindes up a willing vain,</l>
                  <l>Brooks ſhallow murmure, deep flouds noiſe diſdain.</l>
               </lg>
               <signed>S<hi rend="sup">r</hi> D. L.</signed>
            </div>
            <div type="elegy">
               <lg>
                  <l>THe flowre of virgins in her prime of years,</l>
                  <l>By rutheleſſe <hi>deſtinies</hi> is ta'ne away,</l>
                  <l>And rap'd from earth, poore earth, before this day</l>
                  <l>Which ne're was rightly nam'd a vale of tears,</l>
               </lg>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:8734:16"/>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Beautie</hi> to heaven is fled, ſweet <hi>modeſtie</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>No more appears; ſhe whoſe harmonious ſounds</l>
                  <l>Did raviſh ſenſe, and charm mindes deepeſt wounds,</l>
                  <l>Embalm'd with many a tear now low doth lie.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Fair hopes evaniſh'd are; ſhe ſhould have grac'd</l>
                  <l>A princes marriage bed; but (lo!) in heaven</l>
                  <l>Bleſt paramours to her were to be given!</l>
                  <l>She liv'd an angel, now is with them plac'd.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Vertue</hi> was but a name abſtractly trim'd,</l>
                  <l>Interpreting what ſhe was in effect,</l>
                  <l>A ſhadow from her frame, which did reflect,</l>
                  <l>A portrait by her excellencies lim'd.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Thou whom free-will or chance hath hither brought,</l>
                  <l>And readſt; here lies a branch of <hi>Metlands</hi> ſtem,</l>
                  <l>And <hi>Seatons</hi> offſpring; know that either name</l>
                  <l>Deſignes all worth, yet reach'd by humane thought.</l>
                  <l>Tombs (elſewhere) riſe, life to their gueſts to give;</l>
                  <l>Thoſe aſhes can frail monuments make live.</l>
               </lg>
               <signed>M. W. Drumond.</signed>
            </div>
            <div type="elegy">
               <lg>
                  <l>LOe here within this coffin ſad doth lie</l>
                  <l>Religion, vertue, true nobilitie.</l>
                  <l>Ah that a ſilent urne ſhould thus inſhrine</l>
                  <l>What once not mortall ſeem'd, but all divine.</l>
                  <l>More beauty Sparta never did contein,</l>
                  <l>Nor Paphos, famous for her lovely Queen,</l>
                  <l>A beautie chaſt, and chaſt, not to anoy,</l>
                  <l>As was the homicide of Cadmus oye:</l>
                  <pb n="29" facs="tcp:8734:16"/>
                  <l>But baſhfull beautie, harmleſſe chaſtity</l>
                  <l>Such as decor'd that ſometime nymphe, now tree;</l>
                  <l>Hey me my muſe your ſiſters death bemoan,</l>
                  <l>And weep that ſweet Calliope is gone:</l>
                  <l>Thoſe ſounds harmonious ſtrains which to admire,</l>
                  <l>Amazed Orpheus did his lute forbear,</l>
                  <l>Shut up in ſilence, ſhall be heard no more,</l>
                  <l>Which every tripping Dryade ſhall deplore.</l>
                  <l>But moſt of all that ſp'rit ſublimely wiſe</l>
                  <l>Like hers, who from the brain of Jove did riſe,</l>
                  <l>Shinde as that orient lamp, which ſcarſe when born</l>
                  <l>Is ſwallowed in the hudge beams of the morn.</l>
                  <l>Had this ſweet nymphe liv'd in that age of gold,</l>
                  <l>She 'mongſt the Deities had been enrol'd:</l>
                  <l>Or liv'd <hi>Naſo</hi> now to ſee her hearſe,</l>
                  <l>She, not <hi>Aſtraea</hi> had adorn'd his verſe.</l>
                  <l>But what? can heavenly creatures be enjaylde?</l>
                  <l>Or from their native countrey long exil'd?</l>
                  <l>No: All things to their proper center celeave;</l>
                  <l>Nor can immortals from immortals live.</l>
                  <l>Her name the fates to fames report hath given,</l>
                  <l>Her body to the earth, her ſoul to heaven.</l>
               </lg>
               <signed>W. Douglas.</signed>
            </div>
            <div type="elegy">
               <lg>
                  <l>LEt vertuous virgins all with tears behold</l>
                  <l>The faireſt cabin ſtor'd with choiſeſt gems</l>
                  <l>That grace or nature ever did unfold</l>
                  <l>To humaine knowledge under diadems:</l>
                  <l>Of faultleſſe body (here) and guiltleſſe minde</l>
                  <l>The femail ſex perfection confinde.</l>
                  <l>In bloud ſhe might have claim'd unto the beſt,</l>
                  <l>In honour too of none ſhe did come ſhort,</l>
                  <l>In dowry equall with thoſe nobly bleſt,</l>
                  <l>For perſonage of a moſt lowly port:</l>
                  <pb n="30" facs="tcp:8734:17"/>
                  <l>Such bleſſings blooming makes moſt ladies proud,</l>
                  <l>But fully ripe with her, ſhe ſtill was good.</l>
                  <l>Theſe forc'd but fair prerogatives of birth</l>
                  <l>By inward vertue were moſt highly grac'd,</l>
                  <l>Stayd gravitie mixed with modeſt mirth,</l>
                  <l>Humilitie in ſtately palace plac'd</l>
                  <l>Her chaſtitie not ſtaind with any thought,</l>
                  <l>Of heavenly ſubſtance prov'd her to be wrought.</l>
                  <l>No induſtry which curious hands afford</l>
                  <l>Did hirs ſurpaſſe, all ſciences, all arts</l>
                  <l>Her ſex beſeeming, richly her decord,</l>
                  <l>She rather them by full adorning parts:</l>
                  <l>Yet her alas ere luſters foure were told,</l>
                  <l>A winding ſheet for hymens robes enrold.</l>
                  <l>Her fear of God reſpect to parents ſhew,</l>
                  <l>Who never yet could challenge the offence</l>
                  <l>She gave, nor did deſire of youth perſew</l>
                  <l>Beſide their pleaſure, reaviſd thus from hence</l>
                  <l>To the third heaven, ſhe parting with a ſmile</l>
                  <l>Told mans abode on earth was but exile.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>LUte, viol, organ, ſautral, pandal be,</l>
                  <l>Silent, as when in forreſt wilde ye grew,</l>
                  <l>Since cruell death, but pitie overthrew</l>
                  <l>Her, whoſe dear hands made ſweet your harmonie.</l>
                  <l>And if ye ſound bewailing to all ears</l>
                  <l>That ſtroks may ſighs, and ſounds bring forth ſalt tears.</l>
                  <l>A ſnow-like white pure innocence bewrayes,</l>
                  <l>On it black tears, for virgins grief, betrayes:</l>
                  <l>This at her funerall was clearly found,</l>
                  <l>Where all eyes objects black was but the ground:</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>NAtures rich gem, by art moſt orient bright,</l>
                  <l>Of both the honour, parents ſole content.</l>
                  <l>Ladies, yea, ſexes glory, virgins light,</l>
                  <l>Her times delight, than them more excellent,</l>
                  <pb n="31" facs="tcp:8734:17"/>
                  <l>Endew'd with all thoſe gifts which ever' wight</l>
                  <l>Obtain'd on earth: death in the prime hath rent.</l>
                  <l>This leſſer worlds fall (vertues univerſe)</l>
                  <l>Turns hearts, eyes, Verſe, ſad mourners o're her herſe.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>MEn, matrones, maids, come mourn to ſee</l>
                  <l>This matchleſſe match, ſo ſoon to dye.</l>
                  <l>Ours is the loſſe, hers is the gain,</l>
                  <l>When leaving life, ſhe leaves all pain;</l>
                  <l>And doth enjoy theſe endleſſe joyes</l>
                  <l>For worldly tranſitorie toyes.</l>
                  <l>The change is good, great is the gain,</l>
                  <l>When ſhe with Chriſt doth now remain.</l>
                  <l>He now her head, and husband is,</l>
                  <l>She in her life deſir'd but this:</l>
                  <l>And to none other was betroth'd,</l>
                  <l>Belov'd of all, of none was loath'd.</l>
                  <l>Her wit, her vertues wanne her this,</l>
                  <l>Which may be told when ſhe's in bliſſe:</l>
                  <l>Yet being dead, ſhe lives by fame,</l>
                  <l>Her worth doth grace her noble ſteme.</l>
                  <l>But none can fly death's cruell hand,</l>
                  <l>No, not this Phoenix of our Land.</l>
               </lg>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Maerens poſuit</hi> M. R. M.</signed>
            </div>
            <div type="elegy">
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Q<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>id natura potis, quantumve licere venuſtas,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Cuncta,</hi> METELLANAM <hi>dum facit, exhibuit</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Quid genius genio, quid praeſtet virgine virgo,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Iſta</hi> Metellanae <hi>praebuit ingenium.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Cunctorum fruſtra hac ſperata opulentia votis,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Illibata poli gaudet honore frui.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <signed>M. R. Gord.</signed>
            </div>
            <div type="elegy">
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:8734:18"/>
               <head>Laetandum non lugendum paren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tibus defunctae.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>ONimium dilecta Deo, quam flore juventae</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Ante diem extinctam, deflet uter<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> parens!</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Spes ſibi praerept as, &amp; inania vota queruntur,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Plurima quae nimius corde coquebat amor;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Invida quòd nigro clauſerunt fata ſepulchro</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Excultum ingenium, nobile ſtemma, decus.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Expectes thalami, raraſ<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> in virgine dotes,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Dulciloquam linguam, ſuaviſonos digitos;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Ingemat his vulgus, vos exultate receptam</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Coeleſtem in patriam, ſydereaſque domos.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Cernite palmigeram victricem, atque inter ovantem</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Coelicolum niveis agmina amicta ſtolis;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Sponſam agni, &amp; comites laetum paeana canentes,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Cingentes Domini nocte dieque thronum.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Invidia haec, non eſt pietas deflere beatam,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Cui datur aethaereo clara corona polo.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <signed>Gu. Gordonus. M.D.</signed>
            </div>
            <div type="elegy">
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>MIlle fuere proci</hi> Metlanae, <hi>mille neglectis</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Maluit in caſto ſola jacere thoro;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Expers connubii ſine conjuge ducere vitam,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Vincta maritali quàm dare colla jugo.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Innuba Virgo ſolo, te junxit pronuba coelo</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Mors Chriſto, haec thalamis fax magè digna tuis.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <signed>Joh. Gordon.</signed>
            </div>
            <div type="elegy">
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:8734:18"/>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>PArva procelloſo caſa cùm quaſſatur ab auſtro</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Corruit, at levis eſt, levis illa ruina minuti</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Ceſpitis, &amp; junci levis eſt jactura paluſtris:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Splendida marmoreis ſed ſi ſuffulta columnis</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Regia corruerit, quam ſumtu prodigus amplo</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Dives agri dominus, nummorum &amp; foenore dives</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Rite inſtaurandam fecit, quam docta periti</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Condidit artificis manus &amp; mens daedala, magnâ</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Non ſine ſtrage ruent molis radiantia tantae</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Maenia; fornicibus pulchra, &amp; pendentia ruptis</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Culmina; deliciis laquearea tota ſuperbis</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Fulgida; &amp; immenſae ſplendor nitidiſſimus aulae.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Haud aliter ſi fata rudem de plebe puellam</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Interiiſſe ſinent, cui nec ſolertis acumen</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Ingenii, doctae nec blandimenta loquelae,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Dextra nec in dulcem citharae ſat nobilis uſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Nec calamo varias verborum ducere formas;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Cui nihil incultae ſupereſt, niſi ruſtica mentis</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Barbaries, raucique ruens ex ore boatus</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Gutturis indocto; perit hem perit obſita probris,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Et lachrimis indigna piis, indigna piorum</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Fletibus &amp; celebri nunquam dignanda ſepulchro.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Si tamen auguſtae mors forſitan ora puellae</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Solverit in cineres, formam &amp; ſpoliaverit omnem</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Virginis intactae, Lyricam cui Cynthius artem,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Et Jovis ex cerebro Dea mentem indulſit acutam,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Cui linguam Maiâ genitus; proh tota piorum</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Ingeminans gemitus rumpetur turba querelis.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Ergo tuae (pia Nympha) animae dum claudere cipp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Nitimur exuvias gelido, rictuque furenti</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Terra tui dulcem nimium dum corporis offam</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Rodit, inoptatam merito lugemus ad urnam.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Postulat hoc pietas, quis enim tua funera praeceps</hi>
                  </l>
                  <pb n="34" facs="tcp:8734:19"/>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Non ruet in lachrimas dum viderit? ipſa dolendo</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Pallida fit Pallas, Muſarum moeſta corona</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Tristo gemit; tristem matri tua fata minantur</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Interitum, mortemque patri tua fata minantur:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Et fratres tua fata tuos, (bona germina caſti</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Bina thori) &amp;</hi> Sophiam <hi>perimunt tua fata ſororem.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Nobilis heu fulcro domus haec tremebunda remoto</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Tota quatit. Tanti fuerat tua vita; parentum</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Gaudia tu, tu dextra manus, tu dexter ocellus.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>O quam te memorem virgo? tibi multa ſupellex</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Divitis ingenii, mentis tibi multa pudicae</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Signa fuere; habili reſonantia pollice fila</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Sollicitare Lyrae poteras, &amp; mollibus auris</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Chordarum illiciens animos mulcere: tuâ<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan>
                     </hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Vermiculata manu thalamorum vela ſuperſunt,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>(Bezaleelis <hi>opus docti). quid ſingula narrem?</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Mens pia, docta manus, facies formoſa, pudicum</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Pectus, in exiguo ſunt contumulanda ſepulchro.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="elegy">
               <head>For the Mothers moderation in tears.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>WIth grief-torn ſp'rite the worlds redeemer wept,</l>
                  <l>When <hi>Lazarus</hi> his loved kinſman ſlept</l>
                  <l>In deaths black boſome, though he could reſtore</l>
                  <l>Him to the life he had enjoy'd before.</l>
                  <l>Why is it then? I wonder greatly why,</l>
                  <l>The world to thee (dear Lady) ſhould deny</l>
                  <l>Abounding tears, great grief, ſad ſobbing, ſince</l>
                  <l>Pale death hath pul'd thy darling daughter hence</l>
                  <l>More than a thouſand kinſmen; whom from death</l>
                  <l>No earthly power can repoſſeſſe with breath.</l>
                  <l>Mourn then (ſweet Lady) mourn: but which is chief,</l>
                  <l>Learn, learn of Chriſt to moderate your grief.</l>
               </lg>
               <signed>Alexander Hamilton,</signed>
            </div>
            <div type="elegy">
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:8734:19"/>
               <lg>
                  <l>ADiew my Dear, ſince higheſt heavens decree,</l>
                  <l>That I, the harveſt of my hopes in thee,</l>
                  <l>Should not enjoy: Death uncontrolled gives</l>
                  <l>Me endleſſe ſorrow, and the World juſt grieves</l>
                  <l>For thy untimely death. In thy young years</l>
                  <l>Had thou been reft, my mourning, grief and tears,</l>
                  <l>Youth might aſſwag'd: But when time made thee grow</l>
                  <l>To height, what earth could wiſh, or heavens beſtow,</l>
                  <l>In whom was clos'd, wit, worth and vertues treaſure,</l>
                  <l>This makes my grief in mourning paſſe all meaſure.</l>
                  <l>Grave by thy age, but wiſe above thy years,</l>
                  <l>This makes my ſobbing ſighs burſt forth in tears,</l>
                  <l>In having the earths happines I knew;</l>
                  <l>But oh! heavens ſoon that happines with-drew!</l>
                  <l>And cold December which firſt gave thee breath,</l>
                  <l>After twice ten years turn'd, reports thy death.</l>
                  <l>Strange turn of time, the laſt month of the year</l>
                  <l>Should rob me of my firſt-born deareſt Dear:</l>
                  <l>Whoſe qualities were rare, ſo were they many,</l>
                  <l>And good: none equall'd thee, thou paſſed any.</l>
                  <l>For all that's rare, they are but rare in one;</l>
                  <l>But thou waſt rare in every thing alone.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>ENvie and fame are needleſſe to the dead,</l>
                  <l>Becauſe unknown to them: yet let us plead</l>
                  <l>What's ours, even mourning for her ſacred change;</l>
                  <l>Whoſe fame in ſpite of envie lives, though ſtrange</l>
                  <l>Divorce black death hath made: Her noble parts</l>
                  <l>Craves tears from eyes, and ſorrow from ſad hearts.</l>
                  <l>Who as ſhe liv'd belov'd, now dyes with mone,</l>
                  <l>Of kin, of countrey: nor of theſe alone,</l>
                  <l>But all who worth, or vertue did adore.</l>
                  <l>None ſaw her like ſucceed, few paſt before.</l>
                  <l>Thy worth ſo great, our ſorrow muſt be ſuch,</l>
                  <l>Mourn as we can, we cannot mourn too much.</l>
               </lg>
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:8734:20"/>
               <lg>
                  <head>Aliud.</head>
                  <l>
                     <hi>RAra fides, virtus, prudentia, &amp; entheus ardor,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Si poterint poterant te moriente mori.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Indulſit cuiquam nunquam natura, quod in te</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Non rarum &amp; majus laude vel invidia:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Hoc, citius proerepta licet tua funere flere,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>t reſonet famam vix ſatis orbis erit.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <head>Aliud.</head>
                  <l>With ſanctified<hi rend="sup">1</hi>, unſpotted<hi rend="sup">2</hi>, true<hi rend="sup">3</hi>, This one</l>
                  <l>Wit<hi rend="sup">1</hi>, worth<hi rend="sup">2</hi> and vertue<hi rend="sup">3</hi>, To the grave is gone.</l>
                  <l>Moeroris &amp; amoris ergo poſuit</l>
               </lg>
               <signed>M.I. Cockburnus.</signed>
            </div>
            <div type="elegy">
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>FOrma, genus, virtus miranda in flore juventae,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Laudem virginei te ſtatuere chori;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Metellana <hi>domus generosâ prole beanda</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Per te, ſic matrum gloria prima fores.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Sed demiſſa polo pietas in fruge ſenectam</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Maturans, comitem te ſuper aſtra rapit.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Marmora mitte igitur, fuge laudes dicere verſu,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Huic immortali ne moritura ſtruas.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <signed>M. Ro. Balcanquel.</signed>
            </div>
            <div type="elegy">
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>P<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lchra</hi> Metellana <hi>eſt primâ proerepta juventâ,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Et ſecli &amp; ſexus gloria prima ſui.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <pb n="37" facs="tcp:8734:20"/>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Quae teneros opibus mentis praeverterat annos,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Sincerâ ornârat quae pietate genus.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Tota decens, morum candore, modeſtia, &amp; alti</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Artibus ingenii, laude pudicitiae.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Hanc tantùm terris fata oſtendére, quod eſſet</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Non hoc digna loco, ſed meliore frui.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Nempe ſibi propriam ſociavit foedere Nympham</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Chriſtus, ut aeternâ luce beata cluat.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <signed>Alex. Setonius.</signed>
            </div>
            <div type="elegy">
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>SI probitas, ſi forma, &amp; magna modeſtia, &amp; ingens</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Spes hominum quicquam conciliare valent,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Cuncta mihi, thalami nec opes, nec caetera longe,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Vult generum mater, vult pater eſſe ſocer;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Sed mea mortalem ſors dedignata maritum,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Aſſeruit coelo virgineo<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> choro.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Quid nunc forma, genus, quid inania caetera vitae?</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>In ſponſo &amp; Domino cuncta reperta meo.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <signed>M. I. D.</signed>
            </div>
            <div type="elegy">
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>ERgone in illuſtrem potuiſti ſqualida gentem</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Met'lanam hoc mandare nefas? anne invida tanti</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Nominis, hunc tantum potuiſti inferre dolorem?</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Auſa nimis funesta. Tuos ſi flectere ſenſus</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Non potuit generis praeclari gloria, ſaltem</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Plurima tam ſacra ſuadebant parcere Nymphae.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Illa quidem taedas velut averſata jugales,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Qualiter apricis ducebat Delia campis</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Virginibus comitata ſuis, ſic lata ſorores</hi>
                  </l>
                  <pb n="38" facs="tcp:8734:21"/>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Inter honoratas duxit</hi> Metlana <hi>choraeas:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Illa vel aequales quas ſors dedit eſſe, vel inter</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Illa deas luxit, quas ſors dedit eſſe priores:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Caſta, pudica, decens, artes quàm daedala Pallas</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Edocuit, teneram teneriſ<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> refovit in ulnis:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Nam<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> animum fingit ſtudiis nec inanibus aptum;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Et quae foemineum decorant illuſtria ſexum.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Alma Venus Nymphae nec defuit: illa decorum</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Contribuit, placidum<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> ſimul ſuper omnia vultum,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Et pinxit roſeos artus, corpuſ<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> decenti</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Ordine compoſuit, quo ſingula quae<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> referrent</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Et genus, &amp; tantae ſublimia munera mentis.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Cuncta annos aevum<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> ſimul ſuaſere; ſed eheu</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Sola</hi> Metellanae <hi>renuiſti parcere nymphae.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <head>Epicedium.</head>
                  <l>
                     <hi>NYmpha</hi> Metellanas <hi>inter celeberrima, tantae</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Quae fueras nuper lucida gemma domus;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Nympha inter cunctas celeberrima, blanda, venuſta</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Et quae virginei gloria prima chori;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Vive, vale, decus omne tuis, dulciſſima rerum,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Juncta<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> divinis nune fruere uſ<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> choris.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <head>Epitaphium.</head>
                  <l>
                     <hi>STemmate praeluſtris, virtute illuſtrior; unum</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Id mihi prae cunctis nomen honoris erat;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Vixi chara aliis, &amp; chara parentibus, uni</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Quod fueram Chriſto chara, beatafui.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <signed>Patricius Kinalochus.</signed>
            </div>
            <div type="elegy">
               <pb n="39" facs="tcp:8734:21"/>
               <lg>
                  <l>STay paſſenger, O goe not by</l>
                  <l>Till thou behold who here dothly,</l>
                  <l>And help with me to ſhed ſome tears</l>
                  <l>For her; who living had few peeres.</l>
                  <l>A comely Lady truly chaſt,</l>
                  <l>Who in her birth was with the beſt.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Minerva's</hi> ſtock was her deſcent,</l>
                  <l>Which made to vertue her ſo bent;</l>
                  <l>As teſtifies what's to be ſeen,</l>
                  <l>And might be preſents to a Queen.</l>
                  <l>In bountie matchleſſe, and ſo rare,</l>
                  <l>As few with her now may compare;</l>
                  <l>But in her life ſo ſanctified,</l>
                  <l>As in her death ſhe edified.</l>
                  <l>Well, to be ſhort ſhe nothing wanted,</l>
                  <l>Which to the nobleſt Nymphs was granted.</l>
               </lg>
               <signed>M.T. M.</signed>
            </div>
            <div type="elegy">
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>TE matri ſimilem formá, pietate parenti</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Proh dolor! ante diem mors inopina rapit.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Te Deus omnipotens, primis tibi charus ab annis</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Artibus ornavit, quas didiciſſe juvat.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Occidis heu prima prudens in flore juvente,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Atque avi finis ipſa pudicitia eſt.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <pb n="40" facs="tcp:8734:22"/>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Nobilis à proavis, &amp; origine clara parentum</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Clara</hi> Metellana <hi>es; moribus uſque bonis.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <signed>Moeroris ergo poſuit Patricius Metellanus.</signed>
            </div>
            <div type="elegy">
               <lg>
                  <l>WHen thy fair beautie like the bluſhing morne,</l>
                  <l>Which <hi>Ida's</hi> Goddeſſes did all adorne,</l>
                  <l>Shin'd on earths ſtage, and bare the golden ball,</l>
                  <l>Of which for excellence thou reft them all.</l>
                  <l>All that had hearts to wiſh, or eyes to ſee,</l>
                  <l>Became admirers of thy worth. But thee</l>
                  <l>No eye nor heart had worth enough t' aſpire</l>
                  <l>To make his own, till heav'n was ſet on fire</l>
                  <l>With its own Maſter-piece; and took thee home</l>
                  <l>In thy pure virgin white, as here thou come,</l>
                  <l>And left us now (alas) with weeping eyes,</l>
                  <l>To praiſe thy worth, which beſt thy want can price.</l>
                  <l>For why? we truly know it in thy lack,</l>
                  <l>Since all Earth's treaſure cannot buy thee back.</l>
                  <l>Ah me! when nature thus had playd her beſt,</l>
                  <l>Or would, or could ſhe not ſtill make thee laſt?</l>
                  <l>Pencils and pens may thy worths portrait draw,</l>
                  <l>Which to preſume, the beſt ſhould ſtand in awe.</l>
                  <l>But heav'n, that holds thee now a virgin Queen,</l>
                  <l>Among the ſainted ſouls a leader ſeen,</l>
                  <l>Vouchſafes no further good to after daies</l>
                  <l>By want of thee: But if that ought worth praiſe</l>
                  <l>Nature produces, henceforth it ſhall be</l>
                  <l>Moſt chiefly prays'd, for being like to thee.</l>
                  <l>But thy rich mould hath taken ſuch a blow,</l>
                  <l>That now it cannot ſuch another ſhow.</l>
                  <pb n="41" facs="tcp:8734:22"/>
                  <l>Yet in deſpite of nature, death and time,</l>
                  <l>That thus hath reft thee from us in thy prime,</l>
                  <l>Like the Arabian Bird, thine aſh ſhall give</l>
                  <l>A rare invention how to make thee live.</l>
                  <l>Since all that ſaw, or heard, or knew of thee,</l>
                  <l>Shall think their beſt, like thee to live and dye.</l>
                  <l>So though thy earthly part death hath ſubdu'd,</l>
                  <l>All age ſhall ſee thy vertuous fame renew'd.</l>
               </lg>
               <signed>JAMES DRUMMOND <hi>of Millanab.</hi>
               </signed>
            </div>
            <div type="elegy">
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>HAEc</hi> Laderdeli <hi>generoſa nata</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>t</hi> Metellano <hi>Patre, ſic</hi> Setona</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Matre, praeclaris oriunda; ſolo haud</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Sanguine avito,</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Sed magis verâ pietate eâdem</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Jure cantari meruit Camaenis;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Mens ut in coelis, it a fama terris</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Vivat in aevum.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Nobiles ut ſic alios parentes,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Nobiles ut ſic pariterque natos</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Provocet, non tam Baphicove cocco aut</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Murice tinctis</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Veſtibus corpus decorare viſu,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Nuper en vivax breve ſed futurum</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Hoſpitam foedis ſimul &amp; cibandis</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Vermibus eſcam.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Sed mage aulaeis animam decoris,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Mentis integrae celebrare Jovae</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Regiam in terris ſimul, incolamque</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Poſtea coeli.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <pb n="42" facs="tcp:8734:23"/>
               <lg>
                  <head>Aliud.</head>
                  <l>
                     <hi>FAma refert, Chymicos tx deteriore metallo</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Fingere poſſe auri ceu ſimulachra boni.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Nulla</hi> Metellanae <hi>ſuberat deceptio menti,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Hanc nec fucatâ finxerat arte Deus.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Et licet apparet verum, id (ſi credere fas eſt)</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>In ſua poſt rurſum prima elementa redit.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Aſt huic aterni penitis inſculpta figuris</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Vivida imago Dei jam ſuper aſtra cluit.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <signed>DAVID LICHAEUS Myſta Eccleſiae Reriſenſis.</signed>
            </div>
            <div type="elegy">
               <lg>
                  <head>Defunctae proſopopaeia.</head>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Q<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>is neget Aſcraeis dignam te nympha Camaenis</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Quae genus a priſcis nobile ducis avis?</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Nempe</hi> Metellaná <hi>&amp; clarâ de ſtirpe Setonâ</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Nobile ſtemma dedit divus uterque parens.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Nec virtute genus caruit, reverentia vultum</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Finxit, &amp; eximio fulſit in ore decor.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Ingenii mirum tribuit tibi Pallas acumen;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Et dedit ad numerum tangere</hi> Apollo <hi>lyram.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>t pulſare manu, bis quinis nablia nervis,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Sic docta es, pavidas voce movere feras.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Te tua nobilitas, pietas, prudentia, forma</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Fecerunt regi poenè fuiſſe parem.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Dotibus his animi raris, &amp; corporis aucta,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Praeriperis fatis invidioſa feris.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:8734:23"/>
               <lg>
                  <head>Alia defunctae proſopopeia.</head>
                  <l>
                     <hi>BIs duo luſtra meae fuerant modo tempora vitae,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Nobis vita brevis, ſed bene culta fuit.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Inſpice &amp; invenies noſtri pia ſigna laboris,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Relligionis opus ſcrinia parva tenent.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Quàm bene me à cunis clari eduxere parentes</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Vita fuit teſtis, mor s mea ſancta probat.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Diſcite nobilium natae bene vivere quid ſit;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Mors comes eſt vitam ſancta ſequuta piam.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <head>Alia proſopopeia.</head>
                  <l>
                     <hi>VIrgo venuſta decens, animi generoſa, propago</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Lauderi <hi>comitis nobilis, hic ſita ſum.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Non prius, ah! teneris, caepi juveneſcere ab annis;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Quam me praecipitem mors rapit ante diem.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Pollicita ante obitum Patri dare grata nepotem,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Et genero noſtram nobilitare domum:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Praeſcia propoſiti, vetuit Libitina futuri,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Obſtitit &amp; taedis Juno maligna meis.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Aſpernata deas, ſum dedignata maritum</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Mortalem, Chriſtum diligo laeta virum.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <signed>G. E.</signed>
            </div>
            <div type="elegy">
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>SInt aliis ſua forma decens, &amp; divitis auri</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Copia virginibus, ſtirpſque vetusta domus,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <pb n="44" facs="tcp:8734:24"/>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Oruatam cunctis quis te</hi> Metlana <hi>negabit</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Eſſe parem divis, virgineumque decus?</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Divinae ſtodio Sophiae mens dedita, curas</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Spreverat humanas, ardua ſumma peteus:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Hoc tua teſtantur divini oracula verbi,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Sacraque daedaleâ charta notata manu.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Ergo tuas laudes in ſecla ſequentia didit,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Teque vetat pietas poſt tua fata mori.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <signed>M. Ro. Smithus.</signed>
            </div>
            <div type="elegy">
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>EHeu quo moritura? non moraris?</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Non quae nobilitas ſapit capeſſis?</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Hen quorſum didicere tam peritè</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Splendentes digiti</hi> Jubalis <hi>artes?</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Heu quorſum ſuper as manus Britannas</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Scribendo? monumenta quid ſuperſunt</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Virtutis, tacite parem abnegantis?</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Heu quo Scotigenum jubar ſororum</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Migras? ſic coryphaea virgo ſquales?</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Tranſiſque in tenuem volans favillam.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Paulum ah ſiſte, tuis morare paulum,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Qui vitam ſi ne te trahunt miſellam.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Ah non ſiſtis! abis! obis! relinquis</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Sic nos, ſic fere mortuos parentes!</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Sed quid? terra minus reperta digna eſt</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Summi quae ſobolem hoſtiam paratam</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Vivam detineat, Deo ſacratam;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>A cujus pietate, ſpe, fide<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan>
                     </hi>
                  </l>
                  <pb n="45" facs="tcp:8734:24"/>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Mortali ut thalamo carens jugali</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Aeternis thalamis Dei fruaris.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <signed>David Neiſhaeus.</signed>
            </div>
            <div type="elegy">
               <lg>
                  <l>HEr Nature beſt; her moſt complete</l>
                  <l>Had vertue made, and youth moſt ſweet:</l>
                  <l>Moe years could not make her more wiſe,</l>
                  <l>Who here below this marble lyes.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>VIva fuit; poſt fata, mihi (quid plura?) manebit</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Praecipua in terris virgo, ſecunda polo.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>NOw we not mourne, no, but congratulate</l>
                  <l>(O happie virgin) thy thrice happie ſtate,</l>
                  <l>Thou reſts in peace, and we in hope to ſee</l>
                  <l>That day of Chriſt and thy felicitie:</l>
                  <l>Whoſe ſacred ſoule, whilſt bodie once did clothe</l>
                  <l>The world amaz'd, and gaz'd on gifts of both</l>
                  <l>With great delight: becauſe in all thou didſt,</l>
                  <l>The ſecrets of the golden age thou hid'ſt.</l>
                  <l>Yea, bloſſomes ſprang ſo fair and graces all,</l>
                  <l>Which deaths untimely froſt hath now made fall,</l>
                  <l>But if re'niting breath or heat remaines</l>
                  <l>In ſwift-wing'd fame, or in the Muſes veines;</l>
                  <pb n="46" facs="tcp:8734:25"/>
                  <l>Thy bloſſomes ſhall return, and comely ſpread,</l>
                  <l>Though not ſo fair as firſt, yet ne're to fade.</l>
               </lg>
               <signed>Thomas Maitland.</signed>
            </div>
            <div type="elegy">
               <head>Moeſtiſſima Mater.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>THy reſt ſhould me of reſt deprive;</l>
                  <l>Thy joyes make joyleſſe mother live;</l>
                  <l>Did I not reſt in hope to ſtand</l>
                  <l>In joy with thee at Chriſts right hand.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="elegy">
               <lg>
                  <l>BEhold a noble Virgin here inſhrin'd,</l>
                  <l>Within the boſome of this ſacred earth!</l>
                  <l>Whoſe beautie in the bloome, for her deſign'd</l>
                  <l>Approaching <hi>Hymen,</hi> not encroaching death:</l>
                  <l>Yet glorious Nymph, what better change can be?</l>
                  <l>Heav'ns have prepar'd a bridall feaſt for thee.</l>
               </lg>
               <signed>M. G. Prymroſe.</signed>
            </div>
            <div type="elegy">
               <pb n="47" facs="tcp:8734:25"/>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>FOrma deam fecit</hi> Cypriam, <hi>coelo<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> locavit,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Laude pudicitiae facta</hi> Diana <hi>dea est:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Juno Jovis <hi>conſors, morum gravitate celebris;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Pallas <hi>ab ingenio nobile nomen habet.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Si meruere ſuis coelum virtutibus illae,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Nonne</hi> Metellana <hi>eſt nomine digna deae?</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Quam genus &amp; genius decoravit &amp; inclyta forma,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Promeruit<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> ſuâ quae pietate polum.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Nostra ſuas igitur conferre prioribus audent</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Secula, concedant jamque priora novis.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Q<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ae ſuper egreſſa eſt ſexus mentemque, modumque,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Heu</hi> Metlana <hi>perit, ſi periiſſe poteſt.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>In ſua qui ſperant redituras corpora mentes,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Metlanam <hi>nor ánt non potuiſſe mori;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Sed novus exuviis ophis ut revireſcit ademptis,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Sic manet hanc poſito corpore vita nova.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>NAturae in pulchrâ vis ingenioſa puellâ</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Cernitur, artificis grande refulget opus.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Si mentem imbutam quis religione requirit,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Hanc verâ excultam ſi pietate notet,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Non aliam, hunc animum, formam decuiſſe videbit,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Nec formae huic alium competiiſſe animum.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>tque prius ſancto capiebat pectore coelum,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Nunc capitur coelo, perfruiturque Deo.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>CReſcere quis ſacras potuit ſperare Sorores,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Aut aliquid majus poſt Helycona dari?</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Inſtituiſſe novem fert ur Boeotia Muſas,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Reddidit at numerum</hi> Scotia <hi>noſtra parem.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <pb n="48" facs="tcp:8734:26"/>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Jamque</hi> Metellana <hi>haec decima est ſoror addita Muſis,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Aut ſi ſpectetur gratia, quarta Charis.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>O longùm, foelix<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> vale, aequiparanda deabus,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Aeternúmque volet fama per ora virum.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <head>Stanza.</head>
                  <l>THis hopefull maid, made of the <hi>Maitland</hi> mould,</l>
                  <l>Where Natur' Art their induſtrie did ſhow;</l>
                  <l>Timely reſolv'd her graces to uphold,</l>
                  <l>With care to write the works of ſacred troth,</l>
                  <l>And as her years, ſo did her vertues grow.</l>
                  <l>Envious fates untimely crop't them both.</l>
                  <l>Then let this ſerve to make compleat her praiſe.</l>
                  <l>Whom God doth love, they dye in tender daies.</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>QUi modo tot lacrimas, vario tot carmine fletus,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Ante</hi> Metellanae <hi>jure dedere rogum,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Officium fecere, &amp; non fecere poetae;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Muſa ſuum ſiquidem miſit, omiſit opus.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Tanta</hi> Metellanae <hi>moles erat elogiorum,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Cui nec Apollineus par chorus omnis erat.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Quàmque loquendo, ſatis dignè laudaverit un quam</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Nemo equidem, niſi qui ſic ſtupet atque ſilet.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <signed>G. Bellendinus.</signed>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:8734:26"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
